Guide to the Sir William Beauchamp-Proctor Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sir William Beauchamp-Proctor papers
1760-1771
OSB MSS 65
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.55
(2 boxes)
The collection contains letters, addresses, bill and receipts, printed material, and depositions relating to the 1768 Parliamentary elections in Middlesex and the mob violence at Brentford. The letters include routine patronage correspondence as well as items more specifically concerned with the Middlesex election riots, including descriptions of the hiring of gangs by both sides; informants' reports on "Wilkite" plots; and a proposal by Beauchamp-Proctor to John Glynn that they issue a joint declaration against mob violence. Other documents include depositions concerning the riots; copies of addresses to the electors; detailed bills from Beauchamp-Proctor's agents for entertainments in taverns and inns, ribbons and favors, and transportation expenses; and two printed broadsides for Proctor's side.
Beauchamp-Proctor, William, Sir, 1722?-1773
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased on the James Marshall Osborn Fund, 1979.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
SIR WILLIAM BEAUCHAMP-PROCTOR, 1722?-1773
William Beauchamp received an M.A. from Oxford. In 1745 he assumed the surname and arms of Proctor in compliance with the will of his maternal uncle, George Proctor of Langley Park, and was created baronet. He served as M.P. for Middlesex from 1747 to 1768, and last stood for Parliament during the disputed "Wilkite" election of 1768. He died at Langley Park in 1773.
Scope and Contents
The Sir William Beauchamp-Proctor Papers contain letters, addresses, bills and receipts, and other material relating to the disputed 1768 Parliamentary elections in Middlesex and the mob violence that occurred during electioneering at Brentford. The papers include reports on "Wilkite" plots; depositions concerning the riots; bills for expenses by Proctor's agents for entertainment of voters at taverns, ribbons and favors, and transportation to the polls; and a proposal by Beauchamp-Proctor to John Glynn for a joint declaration against mob violence. The papers span the dates 1760-1771, are arranged alphabetically by type of material, and are housed in two boxes. Box 2 contains Oversize material.
Answer. To Mr. Serjeant Glynn, Letter I; To the gentlemen, and freeholders of the county of Middlesex; Patronage, Political; Riots -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1760-1789; Middlesex (England); Broadsides (notices); Beauchamp-Proctor, William, Sir, 1722?-1773; Glynn, John, 1722-1779; Great Britain. Parliament ( Elections)
- Letters, 1769 Jun 23
  - Box, George. ALS to Robert Palmer, Westminster, 1769 Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Re the bill for his services to Proctor during the election and after. Box was hired to defend a supporter of Proctor charged with the murder of a young Wilkite lawyer.
  - Godham, Thomas. ALS to William Beauchamp Proctor, Old Street, 1761 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Requesting Proctor's advice on how to secure the Duke of Manchester's patronage for the place of "Watch Maker to her Majesty."
  - Heaton, Joseph. ALS to William Beauchamp Proctor, [n.p.], 1760 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Requesting Proctor's patronage for a friend seeking a minor place at the Custom House.
  - Heighway, Richard. ALS to William Beauchamp Proctor, [n.p.], 1768 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Re intimidation of voters at the polls by Glynn's supporters.
  - Macquillin, Richard. 2 ALS to Thomas Stone, Southwark, 1769 Jan 10, 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    His investigation of the gangs at Brentford.
  - Plunkett, Philip. ALS to William Beauchamp Proctor, London, 1771 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Requesting Proctor's patronage because "I Voted for You at Brentford without either Fee or Reward." Draft of Proctor's reply on inside pages.
  - Beauchamp Proctor, William
    - ALS to an unidentified recipient, Bruton Street, 1768 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Slight discussion of politics.
    - AL in 3d person to John Glynn, Bruton Street, 1768 Dec 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Proposing a joint declaration against mob violence. Accompanied by 1) text of proposed declaration and 2) AL in 3d person from Glynn, 1768 Dec 3, declining the proposal.
  - Spiller, John
    - ALS to William Beauchamp Proctor, Spitalfields, 1769 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      From an informant, concerning Wilkite plans against Proctor.
    - ALS to W. Tatam, London, 1769 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Accompanying a final payment to the Proctor agent considered most responsible for the violence at Brentford. Spiller warns him against returning to London.
  - Wythes, Thomas. ALS to William Beauchamp Proctor, Lincoln's Inn Fields, 1762 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Requesting Proctor's assistance in obtaining the place of Surveyor of the Window Lights in Middlesex.
- Addresses, 1768 Nov 24
  - To the Gentlemen, Clergy, & Freeholders of the County of Middlesex, by William Beauchamp Proctor, 1768 Nov 24 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - To the Gentlemen, Clergy, and Freeholders of the County of Middlesex, by An Honest Freeholder (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - To the Freeholders of the County of Middlesex, by A Freeholder of the County of Middlesex, n.d.
  - To the Freeholders of the County of Middlesex, by John C. Nokes, 1768 Nov 26 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - To the Freeholders of the County of Middlesex, by A Freeholder in Wapping, n.d.
- Depositions on Brentford Riots, 1768 Dec 10
  - John Kendall, Snr. and John Kendall, Jr., 1768 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Richard McCollister and Francis Riley, 1768 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - John Willson, 1768 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Printed Items, 1768 Dec 10
  - "To the Gentlemen, and Freeholders of the County of Middlesex," by William Beauchamp Proctor, 1768 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Broadside.
  - "Answer to Mr. Serjent Glynn," by "A Plain Independent Freeholder" (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Broadside, 2 pp.
- House Bills, 1768-69
  - Bills to William Beauchamp Proctor or his agents from seventeen inns and taverns, 1768-69 (Box 1, Folder 20-23)
    Arranged alphabetically. Accompanied by one bill for blue ribbons.
- Agent's Bills, 1768-70
  - Bills and statements of account submitted by 8 agents for Proctor, 1768-70 (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
    Agent's bills include legal fees, house bills, transportation expenses, ribbons.
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Oversize, Box 2, folders 30-31
- Transcriptions, n.d.
  - Modern transcriptions of several of the previous items, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Oversize, n.d.
  - To the Freeholders of the County of Middlesex, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - To the Freeholders of the Country of Middlesex, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Agent's bills and statements, 1768 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)